So in this practice,
if you want any results from it, if you
want to practice,
uh you have to be able to face your duka
and not cover it up with some something.
>> Mhm.
>> With some management thing. So you have
to give up things that you use to cover
up your duka.
>> Mhm. so that you can face it, so that
you can overcome it. And these are what
I would say is that's those are the
attachments in your life.
>> Attachments are the coverups.
>> Mhm.
>> That make you feel better in regard to
your suffering.
>> The attachments offer a sense of safety,
um, familiarity, comfort, which all
revolves around kind of you're finding
refuge in it.
Um, so well that's why like the practice
is you know people might a person hears
this and they might think right so I'll
just give everything up overnight
give everything up overnight
sell my house abandon the family do
everything that like all of that it's
like well that still will not
necessarily free you from being attached
to it
so instead you could just take on the
precepts
That's when you're going to feel the
attachments basically being the the
attaching aspect of attachments being
undermined because see you are
undermining now your own safety in a
much more fundamental sense. You're not
letting the senses control your actions.
You're not letting the the the mind
govern your choices and behavior.
Instead, you're imposing certain limit.
And now the mind will resist it. And now
you're going to start seeing why you had
all the attachments the way you did. Why
you were finding conf because you had
access basically
um to things they were pacifying the
mind. They were keeping the mind away
from turning against you. They were sort
of distracting it, keeping it occupied.
So it was bearable, pleasant, agreeable.
So you that's like you could be giving
everything up but if you're not actually
um
undermining that wilderness of your mind
I your own desires
no difference will be made that's why
aseticism is equally ignorable as
sensuality is because your desires
underneath it all remain unaffected
unchanged. So instead of giving everything up
So instead of giving everything up
overnight,
uh give up central cravings. Start by
reducing them. Start by reducing
engagement with them. And you are
actually undermining
the framework of attachment, removing
that um basis
that serves as a safety to you, as a
refuge because it's not truly safe.
That's why there were like many lay
people in the sutras who would have who
who were like anagamis who were freed
from sensuality let alone who had the
right view but the path is the same.
You you have to take on the behavior
that will undermine the relentless
unchecked um desire in your mind that basically is
um desire in your mind that basically is
how these attachments are established,
perpetuated, reinforced
because you wouldn't be
um or if you were attached to your
family say for example and then
uh the family just turns against you. It
just starts making your life unbearable.
your own relatives, your own people
and you have no desire anymore to stay
there because there is no more sense of
safety there. There is a threat now, you
will leave it. You wouldn't have problem
abandoning it. Even if some part of you
ideologically still think but it's, you
know, it's it's my family. Practically,
you'll be doing it out of sense of duty.
Like if you can't get what you want, if
what you want is being taken away, if if
all those things are constantly
repeated, your attachment will vanish.
If the threat of those things is
revealed, dissatisfaction, you will not
want them. So that's where the practice
really is. Yes, you take on the precepts
and some basic sense restraint. Of
course, that's the like necessary first
step, but it's not really about these
grand gestures of giving things up and
abandoning it all. And it's it's about
bringing up those perceptions
of non-ownership, of non-control,
of how everything that's dear to you
will be and is already otherwise
how it could change.
And that's a real that possibility is
real as such. You don't wait for it to
change. The fact that it could change
means implies it's within the domain of
change, which means it's not in my
control. even if it's the way I want it
to be.
And those are the things that would
really make people um anxious and
afraid. But see, as I said before, it's
not the worst type of pain you can go
through. People can take all sorts of
factually extreme pains if they have a
desire to do so. If they have a good
reason to do so.
auster practices,
uh, hunger strikes, starvation, lo like
like choosing death basically out of
conviction, out of desire, out of zeal,
out of inspiration
like like factually unbearable
experience people would take on.
But nobody
would have a desire to subtly on that
right level
uh undermine their own desire
to say no to sensuality to bring up this
doubtful states doubtful states of mind
that they're besetting you and choose
not to give in or try to get rid of them
or act out of them. So that subtle
anxiety unease when you contemplate
dooka and so on in and of itself it's
it's not unbearable. It's just
particularly unpleasant.
And nobody will accidentally choose to
stay repeatedly for as long as it's
necessary with that particular type of
displeasure because you just well first
it doesn't feel like much feels like you
need to do more.
So you want to basically like double
down in these efforts
of of of um of of cutting the ties and
all of that while in reality all you
need to do is just contain your senses
and leave everything else as it is. So
just take on the virtue in terms of
obviously stop the unh wholesome
behavior that proliferates those desires
and then do the same on the mental level
and initially it's going to be a
particular type of confinement felt and
particular type of uneasiness
but that's the worst one as I said it's
because it's s it's because it's
ambiguous it's because it's not so
palpable it's not palpable like the pleasures of
it's not palpable like the pleasures of
the senses and it's not palpable like
the pains of the senses
It's kind of neither here nor there. And
that drives people insane.
So nobody will choose to willingly
stay with that particular uh layer of
not giving into trying to overly think
and resolve this doubt about what should
I do or not giving in and trying to
resolve this anxiety of things could be
otherwise. Nobody would protect that
state of mind because it doesn't feel
right. It doesn't feel like good.
It doesn't feel like good.
But that's the kind of the whole point.
You don't know what's good. You don't
know what's right from a point of view
of puja.
So you want to abandon attachments. just
stay well as the suta says actually the
foremost in outsiders view
is that view that um how was it
formulated I think I might have to
paraphrase it
will not be it won't be for me
>> it could have not been basically and
that which is it's not for me I it's not
in my control
>> so if you somebody adheres to that view.
As the suta says, even without anything
else, they would have removed a lot of
obstructions, which means they would be on the on the
which means they would be on the on the
verge of sapati just with with probably
some like an external utterance in terms
of fixing few things, how to attend to
them because that is how you abandon
attachments. Not by killing yourself, destroying your
Not by killing yourself, destroying your
house, abandoning this. By staying in
the state of recognition, a certain
perspective that things that have arisen
that things that have arisen
did not arise for you. It's just
circumstantially they are. So, and
things that will arise or would have
arisen won't be for you either. It's
impossible basically to cross in the
domain of ownership in regard to things
that are dearest to you. Uh obviously
it's true in regard to things that are
not dear to you. But the contemplation
has to be about things that are dear to
you, not about random stones and trees
and stuff that you don't care about. So
it has to be about stuff that's dear to
me, stuff that I'm finding safety in
that I'm using basically to cover up
that anxiety of non-control.
So keep the precepts until that's
revealed and then protect that. Endure
it how I say like don't try to overly
psychically say oh it's because of this.
It's irrelevant why it is. So what is
relevant is that you are resisting it
internally. Your mind doesn't want to be
with it. Your mind will rather
take on great austerities and great
determinations or commit to sensuality
then stay in that like ambiguous neither
here nor there mildly anxious kind of
undertone of
uneasiness. And that's the neutral feeling the
And that's the neutral feeling the
Buddha talked about.
When it's not understood, it will be
felt like that. It will be felt u
unpleasant. It will be felt
uncomfortable. But it isn't. So it's
only because you're not understanding.
It's only because you're looking past it
which is why you're resisting it.
Contemplate frequently recollect. I mean
there's the literal like the the the
frequent recollection that we're talking
about. One of them was everything that's
dear to me will be and is otherwise like
frequently recollecting that monks as
well doesn't matter
>> what if this thing was taken away from
>> yeah what if this thing is taken away
not like oh how do I deal with that no
it's like how do I remain unmoved in
regard to those perceptions there is no
dealing with them there is no preventing
that one way or the other it's
inevitable so it's like either I refuse
to think about it and then wait until it
happens and then I'll just sort
bear it
or I will think about it and endure that
kind of certain
dissonance of my feeling because it just
doesn't feel right. It's like that's
exactly why it doesn't feel right
because the framework you're holding
wrongly assumed is the framework of
ownership and stuff and this is
discrepant with that. So which one do
you choose then? It's like well if you
have right instruction and faith in the
right instruction you would stick to
this until that framework wrong
framework wrongly assumed frame
framework is dissolved and then it won't
feel wrong it will feel the most natural
thing that which used to be anxiety now it's a
that which used to be anxiety now it's a
quite a liberating neutral feeling
weightless no burden involved
you're untouched